Too bad I can't be in place, but I'm glad we can make the call like this.
Series novel Emilio and forgetfulness is about a retired bank director
who suffers from Alzheimer's and must move to a retirement home.
We get to know several of the others who live in the elderly,
and I am fascinated by your ability to shape their personalities,
But also on how you depict different types of dementia, their way of behaving.
Can you tell us a little about how you prepared to write the story? \ H \ h
Sure.
The starting point for the story was that I wanted to tell you about old age because
My parents had become old, and I also realized that there were very few stories
that had older people in the lead role, not only in cartoon series but also
in movies and books.
There are stories with older people in,
But then they have supporting roles.
It is rare that the stories make us see what older people see.
I decided to draw this story to try to understand my parents better, \ h \ h
I think that Emilio and forgetfulness rather than to deal with an illness
or if dementia is about loneliness, the loneliness of the elderly
and how they again try to create relationships with other people. \ h \ h
Just.
I think you succeed very well in portraying how some of them live in the past.
I have brought with me two pictures.
This is Felix who think he is a soldier \ h \ h
On a Spanish location in North Africa, and do the one of Miguel and Emilio.
I thought the story was a little more varied with these stories.
One of the problems with the story was how to make it interesting.
It is shopping
About boredom, right, about the monotonous life of a retirement home.
It was hard to know how to portray a situation where every day is the same,
And they are people talking.
Then it struck me that I could create variety,
They get a little spinning and think they are somewhere else. \ H \ h
I thought it was interesting for these two reasons. \ H \ h
Yes, we have another example here, Señora Rosalía who thinks she is sitting on the Orientexpress on her way to Istanbul.
It is a pretty comforting picture of dementia I think you are in a remote landscape, \ h \ h
Where you were young.
This page gave me comfort anyway.
Yes, it's a sad story, and I wanted to be a realist, \ h \ h
It is as it is, whether we want it or not, we are getting worse to body and soul
When we grow old.
But I still wanted to find something hopeful, a bright spot in the whole. \ H \ h
This to play with parallel worlds I thought gave it, and
Also a little humor and optimism.
And this person, \ h \ h
Antonia, if she is now named Antonia in your version, she takes refuge there
As a character has been given much more space than I had imagined, a character that would \ h \ h
have a supporting role almost gets the lead role in history. \ h
He grows and changes and eventually gains a completely different meaning than
The one I had thought he would have in history.
In a way, I think that is what is happening
Anyone who takes care of another person.
Many times you forget that person when talking about
elderly homes or a disease like Alzheimer's.
A caretaker, or \ h \ h
only is a relative or friend, the one who takes care of the sick person,
It grows as a person.
It is something many have told about,
caregivers and others whose relatives have been affected by \ h \ h
Diseases with such a long and sad course such as Alzheimer's.
They have said that it also brought something positive with them, that they have discovered things about themselves.
So I thought that all that agreed to Miguel, like \ h \ h
Without noticing it grew by taking care of Miguel.
He took a road \ Hos I had not planned.
The design of the characters, but the one who really worked with the film was the director,
Ignacio is ferrase, and I think he made a very good interpretation.
Some of the
The themes that the comic novel just rub at he deepened.
Just as you said is for example \ h \ h
The friendship between Emilio and Miguel even stronger in the film.
One thing I like I became curious about the movie is that Miguel \ H \ h
talking to Argentine accent, how are it? \ h \ h
It was Ignacio, the director's idea.
His family comes from Argentina and he wanted to make a wink to them. \ H \ h
In addition, it is true that in Spain there is a notion of Argentinians who
Life -happy and happy, they can convince one of anything with their talk,
And it really fit into Miguel as a character. \ h \ h
He is a tremble, and it is suitable for him to have Argentine accent.
Just.
I have read in several places that Emilio and forgetfulness are the work that paved the way for \ h \ h
The series novel in Spain.
Is that right? \ H \ h
I think it is because a number of factors coincided.
It came out in the right moment, \ h \ h
had it come out five years earlier or five years later it had \ h \ h
been completely different.
When it came out, for example, it was so that \ h \ h
The National Series Prize was awarded for the second time, and that it received the serial award \ h \ h
Made it a lot of spread.
It was also a series that reached many
Readers who had never read series before.
It was about such as
Many could recognize themselves in.
A story that so to speak is more typical of series,
which deals with mysteries or superheroes or something like that,
may not reach out to an above audience but this subject \ h \ h
was familiar to everyone, and the series reached out to those who never read series before. \ H \ h
It was noticed in the press and in many other places.
Another important factor
I think was that many general bookstores started taking in comic books.
Previously, in Spain, it could only have been able to buy comics \ hi special bookstores, and to them came almost only \ h \ h
Those who were already serial fanatics.
It was thus difficult to reach outside that circle, \ h \ h
Because series were not sold anywhere else.
But then came luckily was
chains like FNAC to Spain with a French culture and
SPECIAL DEs for series.
Then also other major and less
Book stores to sell comic books.
That the book then
received the national series award, and that it is easy to recommend because
It's a story with a beginning and an end, a so -called series novel \ h \ h
that is easily accessible to all kinds of readers, I think was the reason for that
Emilio and forgetfulness reached out to a serial audience. \ H \ h
I also want to tell you that several of your books are here at the library in Spanish and English,
And of course Emilio and forgetfulness in Swedish.
El Faro, La Casa,
Los Surcos del Azar.
I also know that a new book will come out of you in December, \ Hregreso Al Edén (return to paradise).
Just.
I finished it this summer and it went to print in September, \ H \ h
And on December 3, it will come out.
It is a very personal story that revolves around
A photograph, the only photograph my mom has of her mother,
Who died when she was very small.
She was born in a poor home
after the end of the Spanish Civil War.
That photograph
have always been lying where mothers have the habit of saving
The photographs they keep loved ones, under the glass on the nightstand.
They want them beside them when they sleep.
It is the photograph of my mom that I have seen most times.
I wanted to make a story about that picture and fulfill a dream that I think we all had at some point, \ h \ h
about being able to crawl into a photograph and find out what happened outside the frame, \ h \ h
on both sides of the frame and before and after the photographer snapped the photograph. \ h \ h
Yes, and the critic Álvaro Pons wrote on Twitter the other day that Regreso Al Edén \ H \ h
Together with La Casa and Emilio and oblivion, a masterful trilogy is about the memory.
Do you agree with that?
Is it the memory that is the theme for all your books? \ H \ h
Yes, it is a recurring theme, but maybe not the memory as much as the history of recent decades.
and the search for an identity using the past. \ h \ h
Yes, and this book, Los Surcos del Azar (random track), which will be released in Swedish next year,
Could you say is a restoration of historical memory, right?
The protagonist is a former soldier in La Nueve, a company in free French forces.
Why was it important for you to tell this story of Miguel, a ninety -year -old former soldier? \ H \ h
Well, that was a bit for the same reason we mentioned earlier.
Spain, like all countries, has its features. \ H \ h
In Spain we had a civil war and then 40 years of dictatorship.
Then it became a transition to a democratic system,
And it was not easy to go from being a dictatorship to becoming a democracy.
They made a kind of agreement to forget, we would forget everything that had happened and not search for justice or guilty
Or so, we would all shake hands and forget all that.
Maybe it was necessary to
It would not be a new war or a coup d'état or other problems, the transition to democracy became peaceful. \ h \ h
But, as mentioned earlier, we lost part of our history
And our identity, because one did not talk about the civil war, you did not talk about the dictatorship. \ h \ h
It was thought it was better not to talk about it not to tear up the wounds.
This meant that many stories ended up in the cloud.
Such as this story of
The soldiers who fought with the ninth company.
In any other country I think one would have
named them as heroes.
They never ceased to fight against fascism, they believed in democracy. \ H \ h
They continued war as long as they could, and were in on \ h \ h
to liberate Paris.
They were the first to enter the occupied Paris.
It is a fantastic story simply, but in Spain it was practically unknown. \ H \ h
That is why I thought it was interesting to save it from forgetfulness, this part of the story.
\ h \ h
As I said, they are real heroes, they never stopped fighting, even though they could have it,
They decided to continue to fight to defeat fascism both in Spain and in the rest of Europe. \ H \ h
I also wanted to tell you about it because I like a type of end that doesn't necessarily have to be dramatic.
The same goes for Emilio and forgetfulness.
There are people who, although they know \ hat
They will lose continues to fight and do so with dignity.
Emilio knows he never \ h \ h
Can win against his Alzheimer but is still fighting against it.
And these \ h \ h
Spanish Republicans in the ninth company also fought, they were fighting because they thought a victory over \ h \ h
Hitler and Mussolini would make it easier to then liberate Spain from Franco's fascism. \ H \ h
First one must win in Europe, in order to then be able to return \ h \ h with the help of the Allies
To Spain and restore democracy in the country, but it did not succeed in the end.
This kind of slightly sentimental end I like, they make the stories more important than those who have happy ending. \ H \ h
They make you reflect on the subject, right, to think about what would have \ h \ h
could happen and didn't.
Yes that's how it is.
And I can say that the characters in Emilio and oblivion are still alive for me, I sometimes think of \ h \ h
them as if they were real people.